welcome everybody to the third entry in
nitz's opening lab this is a much
requested and long awaited video that
I'm very happy to be making today we are
taking on a Monumental task we will be
busting the king's Gambit which is
defined by E4 E5 F4 and this is an
opening perhaps the oldest opening in
existence it has been played for right
about half a
century uh it it has not been refuted
and it terrorizes players of all levels
particular beginners and intermediate
players now before we delve into any
specifics I want to get one thing out of
the way which is that the king's Gambit
has not been refuted there is a
narrative that is spread around
sometimes that the king's Gambit has
been discredited and the black is
winning that is completely untrue uh and
the King's Gambit remains perhaps not
close to White's best opening not nearly
the same objective strength as let's say
the R Lopez or the Italian but an
opening that black has to know and an
opening in which black doesn't get more
than a small Advantage if white plays
correctly so it is absolutely an opening
that has to be studied carefully and
that's why I'm making this video this
video will will be about 50 minutes long
so I invite you to set aside some time
have a board next to you and as per
usual you'll have to pause the video
frequently and really engage with the
material to get the most out of it I've
tried to be as thorough as possible
we'll go through all of the sidelines
and we'll put particular emphasis on the
moves which uh tend to have the most air
time in online Blitz Games
so uh those of you who watch my YouTube
channel diligently know that I uploaded
this video uh two days ago and
unfortunately there was a glitch where
the board did not update for the last 20
minutes so I decided to record it again
and hopefully this time it'll be uh even
better and hopefully we will be able to
avoid the glitch this time I'm sorry for
[Music]
that so the king's Gambit is kind of the
father of all gambits it's the Gambit
that people think of when they hear the
word Gambit white sacrifices the king
Bishop's pawn and the point of this is
to facilitate White's control of the
center now the move d4 is a lot easier
to make and once white has control of
the center uh he generally seeks to win
this Pawn back with with the bishop now
the immediate D4 in this position uh has
long been known to be a mistake and
we'll start by going over this move
because some people still play it and
the reason it's a mistake is because it
allows a very nasty check on H4 because
of this F4 Pawn white can't play G3
white has to move his King out into the
open and this is of course no fun so uh
it quickly became known that white has
to start with a move Knight F3 to
prevent Queen H4 and I investigated a
variety of different systems the most
popular move the most commonly
recommended move is G5 immediately
clinging to the pawn I look looked at
this for a while and I think from an
objective standpoint it's a very good
line but unfortunately I think it plays
right into White's hands and it requires
a tremendous amount of memorization and
precision which goes against kind of the
philosophy of my opening
recommendations uh White can play
several different systems uh D4 there's
Bishop C4 G4 and castles this is known
as the msio Gambit white sacrifices the
Knight on F3 and there's also the move
H4 which immediately seeks to undermine
this Pawn chain now in all of these
cases seems to me that white is having
all of the fun even if black is better
objectively and my repertoire is geared
toward primarily Blitz and Rapid players
which means that you won't have a lot of
time to remember you know the only move
you have to find on move 15 to not get
checkmated and so after much research I
came to the conclusion that the most
practical and objectively strong
variation is a move that is not nearly
as common as G5 and D5 it is what is
known as the shallop defense and that is
the move Knight F6
it is named after a 19th century German
master who was not as well known as a
player as he was as an opening
theoretician this guy edited uh what was
really the only opening reference work
in the 19th century the handbook to
shock spiels so this guy knew what he
was talking about he did a lot of
opening analysis and he came up with the
idea of developing the Knight walking
right into the move E5 which seems to
play into White's hands and what's more
the followup here is to plant the Knight
on H5 if if you know nothing about this
system it may seem like black is just
stumbling around and you know the
White's going to win this game in five
moves but I invite you to give this
system a chance I will explain exactly
why we do this and why this system uh is
actually uh incredibly strong both
objectively and practically I think it
essentially takes all of the fun out of
the king's Gambit for white white
doesn't get an attack in any line and uh
it's practical in the sense that even if
you forget a specific move but you
remember the general ideas you can still
get a very good position but but before
we delve into the main line let's invest
a little bit of time into uh refuting
the alternatives to Knight F3 none of
which are particularly good but all of
which you still have to know and we'll
start with the move d4 as I mentioned
black gives a check on H4 and the best
continuation here is to immediately
strike at the center with D5 you
sacrifice the pawn but you get this
bishop out really fast and know this
doesn't win White's Queen due to Knight
F3 but now you aim for very rapid
development and you're basically going
to try to mate this King on E2 you go
Knight D7 notice that black is actually
the one sacrificing a pawn and if white
takes it there's many many good moves
you can simply Castle Queen side here uh
but what I came up with is Bishop takes
F3 check you you can't take with a pawn
you drop the bishop you have to take
with a king now we avoid the immediate
Queen H5 because of G4 we start with
Bishop
D6 okay well what if fight takes now we
don't take back we now we give a check
on H5 white has to play G4 now the queen
travels and takes the pawn on D5 and
after King F2 the only thing to remember
is not to take this Rook this would be
quite bad because after Queen E2 check
black is the one whose King gets really
exposed the queen could get trapped here
this is no fun uh so instead you simply
play Queen takes D6 and white is
virtually lost here because this king is
never going to find a safe square right
it's permanently weak and as soon as
black castles Queen side and gets this
Knight out there will be hell to pay uh
so there isn't much to know here other
than the fact that you just Castle you
get Knight out you can also throw in the
move C5 to open up the center this line
is fairly forced uh so D4 Queen H4 check
and D5 is really really good for black
there are a couple of slightly more
reputable Alternatives here to to Knight
F3 and one of them is Knight C3 I think
this is a variation of the Vienna game
which the first world champion wilham
steinet was known as kind of an expert
in this line he won a lot of games here
and White's point after Queen H4 King E2
is that he's go Knight F3 he's going to
chase the queen away then White's going
to go D4 and eventually the king can
kind of Castle by hand it can go to F2
and people in the 1800s really didn't
know how to meet this steinet won so
many games by doing just that but I came
up with a really cool and really rare
move you actually play D5 anyway here
now you might look at this and say well
that looks like Madness right now I can
take this Pawn with a knight that seems
completely unreasonable uh if if white
takes with the pawn here then you do
much the same thing that you do in the
in the D4 line you go Bishop G4 Bishop d
6 get this Knight out and Newcastle but
what about Knight takes D5 and things
get even crazier here you go Bishop G4
check forcing Knight F3 and now you
simply ignore the threat on the C7 Pawn
you go Knight out to
C6 what Knight out to C6 what about
Knight takes C7 check well we'll get to
that in a second basically you're
threatening Knight D4 check so if white
goes D4 then you are simply winning
after castles Bishop takes F4 and now
Knight after F6 and this position kind
of is an illusion it may seem like
White's doing well White's got all the
trappings of a good position center you
know good development but because this
king is in such trouble all of this
evaporates instantly and White's
position collapses here there's no way
to keep the Knight on D5 and if white
takes on F6 you don't even have to take
back you can play play Knight takes D4
check and uh White loses all of his
pieces you're going to take on F3 and
win the queen and then you're going to
recapture the Knight this is absolutely
terrible for white so white kind of has
to go for Knight takes E7 check Now we
move the king aside after Knight takes
A8 we don't give a check on D4 the king
actually escapes through D3 no we play
Knight
E5 this probably still looks crazy to
you but when I point out what black is
threatening maybe you can pause the
video and figure that out yourself I
think this idea will start to make a lot
of sense now let's take a neutral move
for white let's say white plays D4 the
point here is that white black takes on
F3 and then we take again after King
takes F3 Queen H5 check we win White's
Queen there's no longer a g Pawn with
with which to cover that check after we
take the queen White's position is
completely lost because this Knight on a
is also going to be trapped and the king
is still wide open so that's the main
idea and if you look at this carefully
you'll see that white virtually has no
way to stop this white can play H3 that
doesn't help much you just drop the
bishop back one of the only ideas here
is to play Rook G1 and if black repeats
that process then the rook's going to
cover the check on G4 but the move H3
creates a huge weakness on G3 so we go
Queen G3 and now we're threatening
Knight takes F3 and that is totally
Unstoppable so H3 doesn't work well what
does work by the way if white goes Rook
G1 immediately then you can take this
Pawn on H2 and now white can't defend
this Rook on G1 Bishop takes F3 also now
is a threat because of the pin so the
only way to take the sting out of the
double uh sacrifice on F3 is Queen E1
offering the queen trade now we still
take on F3 here and if G takes F3 we we
still win the queen because the king is
separated from the queen and one very
important detail after King takes F3
Queen takes E1 always be careful and
always make sure to check that white
doesn't have a discover check against
Black's King but that's why it's so
important that the king is on a dark
square if the King was still on E8 after
Bishop B5 check white would win the
queen back and none of this would work
so just an important detail here so in
this position white has to take the
queen and this position has occurred
about 15 times and even Richard report
who's a super Grandmaster played this
this with white in a classical game not
a single person figured out what black
should do here most people went directly
for this Knight with King C8 and King B8
but the best move here is to start with
G5 this is kind of a prophylactic move
you're creating a pawn chain and you're
making sure that white can't use this
bishop on C1 uh as a kind of helicopter
evacuating the Knight through C7 so you
play G5 uh generally white probably will
play D3 here if white plays D4 uh you
don't have to rush to to win this Knight
this Knight's not going anywhere
and here you can start by playing Knight
F6 and targeting White's E4 Pawn which
incidentally he can't really defend
because G2 is going to fall and if D3
now the time has come King C8 King B8
and Bishop C3 no it does not win The
Rook because you have F6 the the one
sample line that I analyzed here and you
don't really have to remember this but
just for the sake of completeness if
fight goes E5 this move makes a lot of
noise but black can meet this with
Knight H6 e takes F6 and Bishop D6 the
point is to get those kings side pieces
out as fast as possible so that F7
doesn't trap The Rook The Rook moves to
C8 not to f8 because of Bishop G7 that's
a fork after Rook C8 we pick up the pawn
on F7 then we pick up the knight in in
any order and then we not only have two
pieces for The Rook which is already
overwhelming but just look at how
dominant our minor pieces are white
simply cannot move here this is winning
for black and this line is quite forcing
so I would spend a little bit of time
and memorize this entire sequence maybe
up until King C8 because it's not
unlikely that somebody is going to try
it and uh you're going to look like a
real Pro when you play the move D5
anyway you're going to make your
opponent think that you've blundered and
it was just a bad pre moove but no it's
all part of the game okay so Knight C3
meets with Queen H4 check and D5 perhaps
the most reputable alternative to Knight
F3 is Bishop C4 and this is also the
only move against which you do not give
a check on H4 very important detail the
reason for that is that Queen H4 check
isn't as strong because the white king
now has the F1 square and as you can see
even looking at this for just a couple
of moments the King on F1 is a lot safer
than it is on E2 so it's not worth
putting this queen on H4 here because
White's going to attack it with Tempo
and moves like D5 just don't come with
the same Pizzazz because Bishop G4 is
not as strong so what we do here is we
simply develop our Knight Knight C6 now
if white goes D4 now we give a check on
H4 and then we play D6 what's the
difference the difference is that after
Knight F3 we can now bring our Bishop to
G4 anyway we can pin the Knight to the
queen this essentially forces a queen
trade and this move d4 actually
compromises White's Center we're
attacking D4 we're attacking C2 and
we're already up a pawn so black just
has a much better end game here so this
is no good and uh the main line here is
Knight F3 to which you respond G5 now
this is not the same as going G5
straight away the position of the bishop
on on C4 uh is is actually not great and
what we're going to do here is we're
going to Fan our Bishop we're probably
going to go H6 to to support the G5 pawn
and this G8 Knight is going to come out
to E7 this is a very solid setup black
is going to be up a pawn for no
compensation so generally white either
castles here goes D4 it probably
transposes into each other castles you
play Bishop
G7 um and if white plays D4 you also
Play Bishop G7 you're never really
afraid of D5 uh because you have this
very E5 square and this is going to be a
recurring pattern so this line tends to
transpose after White Castles or goes C3
so let's look at it in this move order
after you Castle after White Castles you
play Bishop G7 D4 is met with D6 and I
was mostly using the Lees uh player
database to look up which moves uh were
most common online and in this position
the vast majority of people tend to play
C3 in order to butress the the D4 Pawn
so here we respond with H6 and uh once
again most people play Queen B3 if white
plays Queen A4 you can easily Parry that
with Bishop D7 and uh if white plays
Queen B3 then there's a move which has
almost never been played it's not Queen
E7 we don't want to obstruct the
development of the Knight we want to
play Queen D7 first of all we're leaving
the E7 Square vacated and second of all
we are preparing the move Knight to A5
which would completely take the teeth
out of whatever compensation white
claims to have because it would lead to
a very desirable trade there's not much
white can do about it white plays Bishop
B5 then you can simply play A6 uh I
really didn't find anything resembling a
satisfactory move for white here if the
bishop moves back then you can go either
Knight F6 or Knight G7 then you castle
and you've got a phenomenal position
mean this Pawn chain is really really
cool it prevents the Bishop from coming
out it's essentially unassailable if
whatever plays H4 um this is not
dangerous for many reasons one of which
is that you can just uh get this queen
into G4 and White's King is the one that
uh you know that has to say its prayers
so this line is completely innocuous
black has a pawn up for no compensation
the one important thing to remember is
that after Bishop C4 you don't play
Queen H4 check whereas after all other
Knight non- Knight F3 moves you do now
it go goes with that saying that after
Knight F3 don't play Queen H4 check I
hope you can see why now we get to the
fun part now we get to the main line the
move once again is Knight F6 the shop
variation or the shop defense as it is
forly known now right away we pose white
with a dilemma okay white can go E5
which my guess I I think if I remember
correctly is more popular in the
database but white doesn't have to go E5
and he can also defend the pawn with a
knight amazingly the third most popular
move among online games with I think
over 15,000 is Bishop C4 and and this
simply blunders upon PA I think this is
probably the product of a bad pre moove
maybe most of those games were bullet
games but it's important to understand
understand that you can take this Pawn
you can and you should Queen E2 is
totally innocuous on account of Queen E7
and the best that white can do is win
one of the pawns back white can go D3
Knight F6 and Bishop takes F4 but what's
going to happen is that you trade queens
and then you build up a nice queenside
Pawn wedge with D5 and C6 black is
simply a pawn up in the end game this is
the worst outcome for a king's Gambit
player having to suffer Pawn down for no
compensation this bishop is also out of
commission so Queen E2 you play Queen E7
for return to this moment white can also
play D3 and Bishop takes F4 but you do
the same thing you play D5 and then C6
and you're chilling and if White Castles
then once again you go D5 Bishop B3 and
now you can get the light squared Bishop
out to E6 just supporting the center one
cool detail is that if white goes D3
here you can actually keep this extra
Pawn we go Bishop C5 check forcing D4
otherwise white gets forked and then the
bishop drops back to D6 so here white
doesn't even wi back win back the second
Pawn this is virtually resign you can go
G5 or you can just complete your
development by castling and getting this
Knight out to C6 or D7 so Bishop C4
really is a terrible move and the last
thing I'll say the move D3 has been
sometimes played here the easiest way to
respond to this is just D5 and this is
really really crappy for white after
Bishop takes F4 the one thing I will add
is that the computer doesn't love the
idea of taking on e4 for complicated
reasons so here the best move is just to
develop your knight to C6 and if white
goes E5 once again you go Knight H5 and
you do not let white play D4 you shove
that pawn in yourself and this is really
really bad for white this Pawn on E5 is
weak your next move can be either Bishop
B4 or Bishop G4 this is extremely un
uncommon and unlikely to happen but just
once again for the sake of completeness
D3 is met with D5 and if white goes E5
here then you play Knight H5 and you
basically have the main line down a
tempo for white because there's better
than going D4 so there's no sense in
analyzing this and now we get to the
first of the two main moves I'd like to
start with Knight C3 so here we strike
at the center with
D5 okay this poses yet another decision
in front of white white can take on D5
or White can push E5 and the one
clarification that I want to make
straight away is that if you consider
the line E5 Knight H5 D4 you might look
at this and say wait a minute is it
isn't this the exact same thing as E5
Knight H5 D4 in this position the answer
to that is no because in this position
my move and I'll explain this is going
to be D6 not D5 the point is that if we
go D5 I really didn't like the position
after White's move C4 and if you compare
this after Knight H after Knight C3 D5
E5 Knight H5 if white plays D4 there is
no longer the possibility of undermining
white black center with C4 and so this
line is really really good for black
just a little clarification so that you
don't get too confus but before we look
at this I'd like to look at e takes D5
very popular line Knight takes D5 and
now the vast majority of people take
again if white goes Bishop C4 very
common idea you drop oh no you don't
drop the Knight away sorry you play
Queen E7 check uh very nasty little move
white has to go King F1 Queen E2 leads
to a pawn down end game so for instance
here you can go KN C3 and then Queen
takes C2 and no white does not win this
Pawn back because the bishop defends it
very nicely so all of these end games
are really bad for white uh so so King
F1 is is virtually forced uh King F2
loses a piece to to Queen C5 check we
will see this kind of fork again very
soon and so after King F1 now you drop
the Knight back to B6 with Tempo and
here you develop your pieces Knight C6
after D4 I want to make the first kind
of General observation which hopefully
will help you uh understand the ideas of
this line so that you have a fail safe
mechanism in case you forget the moves
so in the shallop defense generally
black castles Queen side uh generally
black has King side that is but in some
of these variations particularly when
White's King position is compromised
black switches gears and says okay I'm
going to give up this F4 Pawn I'm going
to go for quick queenside castling in
order to uh create a very rapid fire
attack on White's King you're going to
see this a couple of times and this is
one example Bishop G4 yes you give up
this PA Pawn but after castling Queen
side you can hopefully see how dangerous
this is for white you're threatening
Knight takes D4 because of the pin and
if white pushes D5 you go Knight A5
White's position here totally collapses
you're threatening to take the bishop
and isolate this Pawn uh you're
threatening to reposition the queen to
F6 this is just such a fun position to
play for black and uh material is equal
which is the best part so this is not
impressive and for that reason everybody
who knows what they're doing plays
Knight takes D5 Queen takes D5 and now
D4 and now a very important thing to
remember you play Bishop E7 here not
Bishop D6 what's the point Bishop takes
F4 ridiculously common right thousands
of games loses the bishop I love these
kinds of moves which are good in and of
themselves they also set a trap so
remember this you're G to I guarantee
you you're going to win some games in it
I'd like to hear that in the YouTube
comments when you win your first game by
uh winning this bishop and hopefully
converting the advantage so why is a
couple of alternatives
this is an important position to to
understand first of all there's the move
C4 attacking the queen and here we drop
our Queen back to D6 so that it defends
f f F4 and if white keeps attacking the
Queen the queen has a great parking spot
on
F6 okay so here we're going to Castle
and go Knight C6 so most people go Queen
D2 and this is the second instance where
we deliberately give up the give up up
the F4 Pawn in order to go for quick
development the move G5 here is totally
fine and black is better
but I didn't love G5 H4 so my
recommendation is Knight C6 Queen takes
F4 and Bishop E6 notice that apart from
the possibility of castling Queen side
white also has these very weak pawns
this bishop is going to park itself on
D5 really an amazing Outpost white is
going to experience a lot of problems
with his Center Queen takes E7 walks
into Knight takes D4 with pretty
devastating consequences whereas after
Bishop B5 Bishop D5 once again white
can't take this Pawn because you take
twice on F3 and the king is toast Queen
E4 Bishop H4 there's going to be mate
and there's going to be a nashing of
teeth as my 10th grade math teer used to
say you're just going to win all of
White's pawns uh together with a strong
attack and if white does neither of
those things then you're going to Castle
Queen side on the next move and quite
possibly you're going to take on F3 and
take on D4 so you might even win a PA
anyway but from a positional standpoint
black has a great position due to this
outpost on D5 and white weak Center so
this is not an impressive line and by
the way if white doesn't go C5 then you
take the opportunity to get this Knight
out and as I've said before D5 is almost
always met with Knight E5 Pawn up no
compensation not much to talk about here
so C4 is kind of an old school move and
it's not very good in recent times uh
more people have been going Bishop D3
but this also fails to equalize and here
we do go G5 and if White Castles we
continue developing naturally Bishop G4
now the main line continues C3 defending
the pawn we just go Knight C6 Queen C2
and we Castle Queens side once again uh
we reap all of the benefits of the
position here we're still up upon PA and
we've managed to Castle now I looked at
this position a little bit and you have
to be precise uh generally white goes
Bishop E4 attacking the queen and
there's a really cool trap here that I'm
just going to mention uh because it's
cool it's not crucial to the video Queen
D6 looks more natural to me than Queen
D7 but her white has a beautiful tactic
I again I invite you to pause the video
and take a shot at it so the tactic
comes out of nowhere it's Knight takes
G5 I was analyzing with an engine and I
thought what has the engine gone crazy
do I need to clean my computer after
Bishop takes G5 no why does Bishop F5
check it forces the bishop trade after
Queen takes F5 white picks up the bishop
and Black's kingside structure is now in
shambles so most people will probably
not see this in a game but the best move
here is Queen D7 and this hinges on a
very important detail it looks like D5
is very scary if you move the Knight
away then you run into Knight E5 but
black counter strikes with F5 DC BC and
first of all the bishop is trapped the
only way to extricate it is to go Knight
E5 now the queen moves up to E6 and
after Knight takes G4 which piece do we
take well we don't take the Knight that
loses the queen we take the bishop and
just look at Black's Pawn Army here this
is almost winning for black white has to
move the Knight back you go E3 you're
going to bring the Rook into E8 white is
totally paralyzed and uh this is really
really fun for for black and I'll take
this opportunity to say that if at any
moment you're not satisfied with where I
stop or you might be looking at the
video and saying you know Daniel
mentions this you know but he doesn't
mention this move or that move I try to
be thorough but I can't cover everything
remember you can call up an analysis
sport on chess.com turn the engine on
and join me in uh analyzing this opening
that's a crucial part that's an integral
part of developing an opening repertoire
because you have a very unique
perspective on which moves are annoying
to you and which moves you would like to
know the response against and when you
play a Blitz game in this variation if
your opponent follows a line that I
didn't mention you want to add that to
your file you want to analyze that and
that is a totally normal process that's
how you enrich your opening knowledge so
this position for instance if you're
uncertain about why black is winning or
why black is better you can you know get
onto an analysis board and just make a
couple of couple more moves okay so this
is an important line um and to to
summarize here if white goes C4 then you
drop the queen back to D6 and if white
goes Bishop D3 then you defend the pawn
on F4 there are a couple of other
Alternatives here let me check my master
file to see what I what I have here so
D5 takes takes yeah I think that's
basically it uh Bishop B2 you also play
G5 this doesn't really substantively
change anything and that's about it so
this line although it was popular a
couple of years ago it doesn't even come
close to
equalizing and now we can look at E5 in
this position remember this is different
from E5 here so keep those lines
separate in your mind Knight C3 D5 and
E5 so we go Knight H5 and this is the
first time that the Knight has landed on
H5 so let me talk a little bit about uh
the the rationale behind this entire
setup Now The Devil's Advocate may say
okay what I don't get is first of all
giving white a big center after D4 and
second of all isn't this Knight going to
be trapped aren't we going to have
constant problems with discoveries and
this just looks impractical well wrong
on both points because first of all
white driving these pawns further into
the center doesn't mean anything black
can work around these pawns and very
often black can make the move F6 to
undermine White Center so in the king's
Gambit white actually doesn't want to
push these pawns out too early to
overextend himself as for the Knight
being trapped it's not trapped for two
reasons most of the time we will go G5
and the Knight will have an escape hatch
uh through G7 and later on to E6 or or
F5 which is a phenomenal Square in
certain positions you can simply play
the move G6 not only does that defend
the Knight but that also creates in the
case of an emergency um leave your
possessions in the airplane case of an
emergency uh we still have the G7 Square
for the Knight so this is an illusion
and at no point can white really move
this Knight away from F3 because of the
deadly possibility of Queen H4 check now
in this position we continue our
development with Knight C6 I looked at a
couple of moves here uh Bishop E2 is
possible and now you go G5 uh this seems
to walk into a tactic but if you just
look one step further this is another
case uh where you give up the pawn in
order to get quick development and
Castle Queen side once again the reason
we do that is because White's King is
now very very compromised now the line I
looked at here is Bishop F3 if Queen F3
then you can take the pawn on D4 so
don't forget that pawn is is weak and if
Bishop F3 we blast open the center F6
Knight takes D5 castles and after C4 F
takes E5 once again White's position is
on the verge of collapse and the king is
is going to be toast in in the long run
so uh Bishop B2 you respond with G5 and
if Bishop B5 first we go A6 to force the
bishop to make a decision uh if Bishop
A4 once again we can start with Bishop
B6 and then we go G5 phenomenal position
for black later we can go Knight G7 and
Knight F5 and I'll talk more about these
positions a little bit later uh and if
white plays Bishop takes C6 we play B
takes C6 we're not worried about this
Pawn structure being slightly damaged in
fact the D5 Pawn is now even better
supported than before there goes G5 and
if Knight E1 there goes the Knight to G7
H4 can always be met with H6 you're
never worried about that and uh the one
game Contin G3 FG and white is look just
look at this King we're up two pawns
Knight's coming to F5 uh you know I
would pause the video in one of these
positions just you know make make sure
that you understand why these positions
are so overwhelming so my suggestion
would be maybe take a look at this
position uh and just fully understand or
sorry Bishop B2 G5 fully understand all
of the ideas what I mentioned about
Knight G7 uh and you can always slow
down and take the higher level view the
only other move here that I looked at
here is Bishop D3 and once again you go
G5 if castles then you can push this
Pawn all the way down to G4 because the
bishop has intercepted the Queen's
control over D4 and uh if if Knight D1
then Knight takes D4 is absolutely
absolutely crushing uh so I looked at H4
here but now we go G4 Knight G5 and once
again we can simply take the pawn on D4
now we're two pawns up and we've kept
all of the advantages of the position so
none of these moves are dangerous uh and
so Knight C6 I think simply refutes uh
this this subv variation I didn't see
anything remotely appealing that that
white could do and that finally brings
us to the main move E5
E5 Knight H5 and virtually everybody is
going to play D4 now the interesting
thing is that uh John Shaw who is a
Scottish Grandmaster uh and a noted
opening expert he wrote a very good book
on the Kings Gambit I think a couple of
years ago and I consulted that book to
see what he recommends against this line
sha uh recommends a rare move Bishop E2
in this position essentially trying to
Target this Knight as quickly as
possible and uh the other person that I
want to credit is a national master
named Joseph Tron Joseph uh created a an
excellent chessable course uh on playing
against the king's gamut where he
recommends the shop um now I didn't
consult his chessel course too much uh
but I looked at some of his
recommendations his analysis is
excellent I highly recommend it uh as a
supplement to this video I'll link it uh
in the description below and I'd like to
credit Joseph uh for coming up with an
excellent recommendation against Shaw's
move which sha himself does not consider
once again we go Knight C6 but the the
Crux of this is that after castles if
white goes D4 then we go with the
immediate D6 this is going to transpose
because in this position white is
nothing better to do than to Castle so
if castles here we go D6 white kind of
has to go D4 if e takes D6 in any such
position it's it's bad because our
Knight now has an easy Retreat back to
F6 so after D4 we go G6 I mentioned this
move sometimes we go G5 sometimes we go
G6 now you might ask well why not G5 the
reason G5 is bad here consists in the
move D5 this is kind of Shaw's Point
Knight takes E5 obviously loses a piece
and White's pawns really can cause some
damage if they get to E6 so here we go
G6 and uh I think this takes the sting
out of this line e takes e takes D6
excuse me take a sip of
coffee now I feel like I got m
drink my water pause the video now so if
if white doesn't take then then Yan C
the bishop e e takes D6 C takes D6 and
we're just better uh yet again D5 is met
with Knight E5 and there's a forcing
line here white can win the pawn back
takes takes and takes but uh we can
throw in a check and When the Smoke
Clears we shift Our Queen to G6 and we
just have this Monster Pawn chain on the
on the king side The Bishop's coming out
to F5 and in the event of a queen trade
I mean hopefully you can see that this
position is absolutely overwhelming for
black so this is not dangerous and
instead of Knight C3 if black white
takes immediately then we take with a
bishop and after Knight C3 uh we can
Castle trulson stops his analysis here I
found them move Knight E5 interesting
attempt to muddy the waters but now we
drop our Knight back to G7 here's the
idea in action and although white can
win the pawn back by taking on C6 and
taking on F4 his uh relief is shortlived
our Knight travels to E6 and causes uh a
lot of problems Bishop D6 Queen D6 and
white cannot defend this pawn and if
white tries to be cheeky with Bishop B5
then we we grab it and we go Queen G5
and once again the pawn cannot be
defended this is probably White's best
line objectively but at the end of it
he's down a pawn he's clearly worse and
this would require white to play
accurately for for 14 moves so not a
great outcome and so Bishop E2 thank you
to Joseph for finding the move Knight C6
and now we get to the move which you're
going to see a lot more frequently and
that is D4 okay so I vacillated for a
while on D5 versus D6 Dron recommends D5
But ultimately I was not able to find
anything too satisfactory after C4 and
that is why I settled on
D6 I I also like this move because it
virtually forces white to find an only
move every other move and white is in
huge trouble the only move that gives
white a tenable position is Queen E2
which is virtually never played in
online games in over theboard chest
among Grand Masters yes GMS no to play
Queen E2 but most people online make one
of two moves and both of them are really
bad most people play Bishop C4 this
walks right into what we want to do now
we go D5 and everything changes after
Bishop D3 G5 we have one a Tempo so the
move C4 is totally not dangerous so for
instance after Castle Knight C6 if white
white generally goes C3 if white goes C4
we capture on C4 now we make a really
cool move Rook G8 you might look at this
and say whoa whoa whoa whoa what about
D5 this looks scary it's actually not we
go G4 counter striking on the king side
and although this may look a little
chaotic white is actually just
completely lost here and I'm going to
knock your socks off with a cool line in
just a second but here if white plays D
takes C6 trade Queens take on F3 don't
forget the black is already a pawn up
and now the attack against White's King
has grown totally devastating now if
white goes C3 in this position then we
we develop our Bishop and one cool line
that I considered was B4 trying to get
something going on the queen side G4
forcing the Knight back and now A5
undermining the queen side but what's
the idea what does black do after B5
good spot to pause the video and try to
figure it out there is a beautiful idea
here take on E5 after d takes E5 the
idea of going A5 has been revealed we
now have access to the C5 square and now
we sack another piece on G3 and
hopefully you see where this is going
this is a common mating pattern our
Bishop controls G1 there's nothing white
can put on this diagonal that can't be
captured and queen H5 or H6 Checkmate is
totally Unstoppable it is inevitable
white loses so just one of many really
really cool lines that I think show how
fun this uh variation is to play that
Knight on H5 has some teeth it doesn't
just passively sit there defending F4 in
certain situations it can sacrifice
itself on G3 and so uh it turns out that
this bishop C4 move is is just bad we we
just go D5 D5 followed by G5 and then we
develop our pieces Knight to C6 Bishop
to E6 other Bishop to E7 and at any
moment we can drop our Knight back to
G7 okay so what about e takes D6 well as
I've already mentioned this walks right
into Black's hands Bishop takes D6 uh
and now we develop normally castles
castles Bishop G4 and Bishop G4 is
always a good move here because after H3
we don't have to take the Knight we drop
our Bishop back and we have induced H3
creating a massive weakness on G3 uh
where we can now Inson our Knight so
black is a pawn up and as my coach used
to say black has the extra pawn and he
has the compensation so we're doing
great here and the only other move that
I saw played with any regularity online
is Knight C3 but this ignores the idea
of D6 we play D takes E5 and white is in
a tough spot because Knight takes C5
loses to Queen H4 check D takes C5
allows the queen trade which is
obviously really good for black the only
uh tenable move is Queen E2 but now we
get our Bishop to
G4 and after Queen takes E5 check we
play Bishop E7 and there's this one
detail that I would advise that you
memorize after Knight D5 you have to
know the move Knight C6 and its idea is
not hard to understand after Knight
takes C7 King f8 there is no way for the
queen to keep protecting the Knight the
queen has to drop back and white loses
the Knight so no we're not blundering a
fork here uh we're we're just seeing one
step ahead so this is good for black and
and uh Knight C3 just D takes E5 and so
that leads me to what I would really
call the only serious move in this
position and that is Queen E2 but again
I think you're unlikely to face it I
think you're more likely to face Bishop
C4 or Bishop E2 and as a sneak preview
uh on the opening videos that I will be
making I'll be making a series of videos
very soon where I actually recruit
people from my twitch community and my
supporters to play a series of games
with me in the same opening so I ask
them to basically play the Kings Indian
in 10 consecutive games and then I'll
put out a video where I'm actually
putting uh this theoretical information
to practice and hopefully that'll give
you a slightly different perspective and
hopefully it'll help solidify not only
the theory but also the general ideas
because I'm sure that I'll be facing
lines that I haven't
covered okay so let's get to Queen E2
now we take on E5 and once again Queen
takes E5 anytime we can trade Queens
like this we should and black is better
Bishop E2 we don't have to rush with
Queen takes C5 first we develop our
Bishop to G4 and uh if Bishop takes F4
another example of a situation where we
sacrifice back the pawn but we have a
huge initiative if the bishop drops back
then who Knight comes into B4 it drops
back down to D5 and what I want you to
notice here is that the lack of the F2
Pawn really hurts white in more than one
way it doesn't just weaken the king it
also doesn't allow the bishop on E3 to
be anchored now white has to move the
bishop back and the Knight comes in to
F4 so White's position is really
discombobulated as a result of the F
Pawn not being there meanwhile if Bishop
takes C7 then we chase that bishop and
the bishop literally has nowhere to go
Bishop G3 we grab we grab and we grab
and we're going to grab on C2 with uh
totally devastating effect so Queen
takes E5 we cover with the Queen the one
important thing here is not to take the
queen straight away because then white
takes back with a knight and attacks
then on H5 here we got to be patient and
get your your Bishop out to to G4 um I
guess white can play H3 here which I
didn't analyze but now you can grab the
queen because obviously if Knight takes
E5 you're going to Fork him in the end
and if D takes E5 now we can drop the
bishop back and once again Knight G3 is
going to be very very strong so that
really only leaves us with Knight takes
E5 D takes E5 Bishop G4 just looks
terrible for white H3 there's always
Knight
G3 after Queen takes E5 uh sorry after
Knight takes E5 as as you might imagine
you give a check on H4 okay why is it
one
moment I guess the the gods don't want
me to complete this video okay I think
we're good Knight Knight takes E5 Queen
H4 it kept reverting to that position
maybe uh somebody hacked this analysis
board he's like Daniel you haven't
explained that well enough so Queen H4
check now at first sight this just looks
great for for black right because as
we've already established G3 is almost
never possible in these positions and so
if White has to move the king away well
well that's no good right we can just
play Bishop B7 and you know then we
castle and White's position is terrible
uh but it turns out that white can play
G3 here and the point is that after F
takes G3 white uses the discovery and
wins Black's Queen before we have a
chance uh to win White's Rook white goes
Knight G6 check no problem you might say
don't we have the move Knight takes G3
and we do you do play Knight takes G3
and uh now no Discovery works because
because the queen is attacked so white
has to play hg3 and we play Queen takes
H1 now I would say that this is the only
variation in this entire line which one
could refer to as messy and that doesn't
mean it's bad and that doesn't mean you
can't tackle it I would just suggest
that you spend you know maybe an hour
reviewing this segment of the video and
really making sure that you understand
every move that is played from this
point on and that you basically have it
memorized this is really only one of two
lines that I think you should memorize
now first things first thing to get out
of the way white does the move Knight G6
check Bishop B6 Knight takes h8 and yes
white is a piece up but he's also
completely lost because of White's total
lack of development and also the fact
that the Knight on h8 is stranded and
the fact that black has a bunch of extra
pawns on the king side so here we play
Knight C6 then we take on G3 and you
know white offers a queen trade we
decline it and our next couple of moves
are going to be Castle's Queen side then
we're going to get the bishop out not
only are we going to win the Knight back
but White's King is absolutely
devastated so this is another good
position to dig around in you can set
this up and just make a couple of moves
and convince yourself that this is
completely and totally winning for Black
by the way D5 walks into Bishop takes D5
and that is why we put the queen on H4
we're going to promote on the next move
and make a second Queen okay so instead
of Knight G6 check white has to be
patient and the only move is Bishop
takes F4 now we make another move which
which might seem puzzling we play Bishop
D6 you just have to remember that white
doesn't actually have any dangerous
discovery
once again if Knight G6 check we respond
in exactly the same way Bishop B6 Knight
takes h8 and the same principle we take
on F4 we go Knight C6 we castle and we
win the Knight back and then we're we're
going to be up a pawn and we're going to
have a long-term attack on Whit's uh
White's King so this is really really
bad after Knight D2 the one thing i'
throw in is that white is ready to
Castle Queen side so you can throw in a
check on
H4 and um you can trade Queens take on
h8 and this should be winning for black
up a pawn you have an outside passer so
once again Knight G6 check is not
dangerous here and so uh the people who
know what they're doing uh are going to
go Knight C3 but for context this has
only occurred in over the board chest
twice uh and one of those games was
nepom Nishi against fuja from a recent
tournament so nepo is one of the only
top Grand Masters who still likes to
play The King's Gambit on occasion and
yes he knew what to do here but uh even
if white plays perfectly as you'll see
he's going to have a worse end game
finally we castle that's why we played
Bishop D6 well white is nothing to do
but to Castle himself now the threat
here that we have to deal with is Bishop
G2 so let's if we make a random move we
lose our Queen Bishop G2 Queen H2 Rook
H1 and Black's next move is aimed
against Bishop G2 we go Bishop H3 we
beat white to the punch all right so
Bishop G2 doesn't work anymore and uh
our point is that we're going to get our
Knight out to C6 and we're just going to
be up in exchange we're going to
consolidate and in this position the
only move that en Ables white to stay in
the game is Knight takes F7 again a move
that somebody really has to know uh I
looked at this online and a couple of
people so if white takes on H3 and then
plays Queen E4 this is a tricky attempt
because Rook H1 is a threat and then
you're going to have problems with H7 so
here uh you bring the queen back to E6
and this is a paper tiger you just go
Knight D7 and black has Consolidated his
extra
exchange a couple of people have gone
Knight E4 which is a goodl looking move
right centralizing the Knight doesn't do
anything we just go Knight D7 lot of
pieces that are hanging but in reality
uh all of this favors black if if uh
well if G4 you go Knight out to F6 uh
forcing the trade and White's position
collapses here just note that this
construction is totally self-sufficient
there's no way for white to put pressure
on either of these pieces and at the
right moment you can take on F1 and hit
the queen and then bring your queen back
that's really the point and if Knight G5
here's a case in point you take on E5
then you take on F1 and then you bring
your queen back to C6 and you're
completely winning we're up in exchange
and a pawn so none of the moves other
than Knight takes F7 are dangerous the
point of Knight takes F7 is to expose
Black's King so that you can later get
this bishop out with check what we do
here is we take on F4 now we do not take
on F7 never play this move because
you're going to get checkmated and do
not take with a king because you might
not get checkmated but you're definitely
going to lose your queen and probably
even more than that instead you play
play the very calm move Knight D7
getting her Knight out if white moves
the Knight away then you know the drill
Bishop takes F1 uh Rook takes F1 Queen
C6 there's no check on C4 you're just
going to play H6 and Rook E8 and we're
completely in charge and up an exchange
so Queen C4 is the only only move now we
take on F7 and the point of this is
revealed white takes on F7 and then
plays Bishop C4 and check and the smoke
is cleared white is going to win the
queen back but guess what we drop our
Bishop back to E
white can't take immediately because he
loses the bishop but after Bishop takes
E6 Rook takes E1 and Knight F6 okay
white has found 20 computer moves you
applaud you take your hat off and guess
what black is still better black has a
clear advantage in the end game because
we are the ones with a past H Pawn and
white is the one with uh incredibly weak
pawns particularly the one on F4 which
is easy to attack so I left the computer
running here for a while the engine
tends to say that white can hold the
draw with accurate play
but I think this is a pretty darn
positive outcome particularly because
white has found all these moves and for
the king's Gambit player to play a worse
end game is probably you know worse than
eating dirt for the rest of their lives
so so just remember this line let's go
through that one more time um if Queen
E2 you play D takes E5 you give this
check now first Pitfall don't take with
a pawn take with a knight and really the
moment where I think a lot of people
might be confused is here you don't
there's a temptation to block the queen
but but you don't do that you go Bishop
D6 and it's important to understand why
it's not dangerous to lose that Rook on
h8 if white keeps developing you castle
and the third thing to remember is not
to allow Bishop G2 but rather to play
Bishop H3 and if somebody knows Knight
takes F7 then you take on F4 you make
the C move Knight D7 and uh you get this
liquidation don't forget to play Bishop
B6 here right otherwise white takes on
H1 and sort of skewers the pawn and you
play Knight F6 and you're better so that
essentially concludes uh my presentation
of the shallop defense let's uh do a
quick overview of what we went through
so after e takes F4 we went through the
alternatives to Knight F3 we looked at
Knight C3 Bishop C4 and and D4 you play
Queen H4 check against D4 Knight C3 but
not against Bishop C4 because the king
will have the F1 Square then we started
looking at the actual shallop defense
and I will add some a detail I forgot to
mention is that the first mention of
this move uh was not by shop but by yes
ruy Lopez can you believe it in his uh I
think this was written in I have to
check my source let me see I wrote this
down Ru Lopez uh the originator of the
Spanish game he was a priest but he also
wrote one of the first chess manuscripts
it was a it was a chess instruction book
I think it was the late 1500s but don't
quote me on that uh so he made mention
of this movie he analyzed a bunch of
openings and R Lopez seemed to think
that Knight F6 is bad because after E5
Knight h
5 um he didn't even consider Knight H5
he I think he only considered like
Knight E4 and then the Knight gets
tossed around um or or no no he did and
he mentioned that after G4 black is on
pant so one of the coolest things uh
that the author mentions this is a book
called The Classical era of modern chess
it basically traces the very first books
written about Chess and talks about what
they talked about and uh there's a
debate about when on pant entered common
chess rules and this is a very important
piece of evidence so this line we're
talking about is also used by chess
historians as evidence that anasan
existed in the late 1500s because Ru
Lopez made mention of it G4 would have
trapped the Knight were it not for
anasan I don't remember exactly why he
thought this was bad but he didn't like
it neither did polario who was an
Italian master uh who wrote a manuscript
around the same time as R Lopez and Shop
was only the third or fourth player to
actually play this in over the board
chess the first player to play this was
uh very imposing name and I'm sure I'll
butcher the pronunciation count Conrad
vitum vonat who was the heir of a noble
family in Germany uh so he was the first
person to to play Knight F6 and and he
did put the Knight on H5 but shop really
codified this he analyzed it and so the
N the line Bears his name little piece
of chest trivia there so Knight F6 we
looked at the two main moves Knight C3
and E5 if Bishop C4 you can grab the
pawn um after Knight C3 we strike at the
center with D5 remember the key detail
after E5 Knight h H5 D4 we can simply
develop because white doesn't have the
move C4 uh we also looked at e takes D5
and then essentially you cling to this
Pawn in most cases and sometimes you
Castle King side sometimes if you feel
that White's King is particularly weak
you can Castle Queen side and finally we
looked at the main line E5 Knight H5 D4
now do not play D5 because it allows
nasty moves C4 although if you look at
Joseph TRS and chess of course I'm sure
that he does some very good work on D5
as well but the move is D6 the idea is
to quickly undermine White Center
against Bishop C4 now you play D5 with
Tempo and you know the drill Knight C6
G5 Etc against almost all other moves
you play D takes C5 including the main
line Queen E2 D takes C5 and even with
best play White ends up slightly worse
all right ladies and gentlemen that was
a pretty long video let me check how
long it was it was 51 minutes that's
about exactly the same length as the
first time I recorded it I hope to God
that the board transmission bug did not
make another appearance I'll be
reviewing that right after I click stop
record but if you've made it to this
this far thank you so much and
congratulations it is not easy to sit
through an opening video this long but
again my philosophy of my channel and of
the opening videos is that I'm offering
you this invest an hour and you will
have a repertoire that might very well
last you a lifetime so as usual please
feel free to leave comments leave
questions uh in the comments below and I
will try to get to as many of them as as
I can and finally I have started a
patreon so by popular demand I do have a
patreon now I'm going to link it in the
description I just want to make it clear
zero obligation this is not me meant to
pressure anybody and uh you know not and
none of my content is now going to be
behind a pay wall but the only thing I'm
going to offer as part of one of the
tiers is uh some people ask for pgn's I
will have a PGN available for uh for
patrons at all tier so feel free to
check it out I greatly appreciate the
support you guys are all awesome but
please don't feel any obligation uh to
to become a patron uh or do that I I
love everyone equally but just wanted to
put that out there for your information
so the link will be below well I hope
you enjoyed I hope you now are armed
with the tools you need to kill the
Kings Gambit to crush it with a K and uh
I will see you in the next video thank
you so much and goodbye
[Music]